2013年6月26日
拿这么多干嘛  说了只能带一个箱子
What's all this? I said one suitcase.
我需要各种备选衣服  杰
I need choices, Jay.
在哥伦比亚没必要那么讲究吧
Colombia's not one of your more formal nations.
有钱人坐在躺椅上都行
The guy on their money is sitting in a lawn chair.
真不敢相信我的小宝贝要离开我了
Ay. I cannot believe that my little baby's leaving me.
我忘了关楼下的玻璃门了
You know, I left the glass doors open downstairs.
所以现在你真正的宝贝可能正在离开你呢
So right now, your actual baby may be leaving you.
睡袍只能带一件
One robe.
我猜第二天早上大家都要
I guess we know what everyone
议论我连续穿同一件睡袍了
will be talking about my second morning there.
曼尼要去歌洛莉亚老家待一个月
Manny is visiting Gloria's family for about a month, I hope.
我得趁歌洛莉亚情绪崩溃
I just gotta get him on a plane before
改变主意前  把他送上飞机
Gloria has a meltdown and changes her mind.
因为如果不把他送去哥伦比亚
'Cause if he doesn't go to Colombia,
整个哥伦比亚就要找上门了
Colombia comes to me.
先前的惨痛教训历历在目
It happended before.
我的天啊
Oh, my god.
-天呐  -怎么啦
- Oh, my god! - What?!
是米奇尔  我们赢了
Oh! It's mitchell. We won.
太好了  赢什么了
Ay, that's great! What we won?
太棒了  我们等了那么久
It's fantastic. We've waited so long.
赢什么啦
What did we won?!
最高法院裁决判定同性婚姻合法
The supreme court ruling. Gay marriage is legal.
恭喜恭喜
Ay! Congratulations!
谢了  歌洛莉亚
Thanks, Gloria.
能让小卡接电话吗
Can I talk to Cam?
好  等下
Uh, yes. Hold on.
谢谢  谢谢  是的  是米奇尔
Thank you. Thank you. Yeah, it's Mitchell.
喂  说
Hi. Hey.
我得挂了  你能相信这终于成真了吗
I gotta go. But can you believe this finally happened?
是啊  太棒了  晚上要庆祝一下
I know. It's amazing. We'll celebrate tonight.
-我爱你  -庆祝什么
- I love you. - Celebrate what?
杰  坐稳了
Oh. Well, Jay, hold on to your hat.
从今天开始  在加州
But as of today in California,
法律认可同性婚姻啦
it's legal for a man to marry another man!
他吐了
Ew. He threw up.
他只是需要点时间来接受  亲爱的
He just needs some time to get used to the idea, honey.
太棒了  小卡
It's so great, Cam.
是啊  真替你们开心
Yeah, I'm happy for you guys.
歌洛莉亚  曼尼需要出生证明
Gloria, Manny needs his birth certificate
才能重新入境
to re-enter the country.
知道在哪吗
Any idea where it is?
我不知道
I don't know.
对哦  他今天就走了  你一定很不舍
Oh, that's right. He leaves today. You must be a wreck.
她没事的  她很坚强
She's not a wreck. She's a rock.
找过了  没在保险箱里
Now, I looked, and it's not in the safe.
莉莉上周第一次在朋友家过夜
This one had her first sleepover last week.
我鼓励自己要坚强  挺过了一晚
I just had to tough my way through it.
他半夜去把我接回家了
He picked me up in the dark.
哪里都找不到出生证明  杰
I can't find that birth certificate anywhere, Jay.
也许这是个预兆
Maybe it's a sign and --
是个预兆提醒我们要重新讨论
It's a sign we need a refresher meeting
保险箱里应该放什么
on what goes in the safe.
先给你透露一点  不能放鞋
Here's a preview -- no shoes.
我上网查了
Look, I looked online,
我们可以去法院要个复印件
and we can get a copy if we go to the courthouse.
就这么办  上车
That's what we're gonna do. In the car.
我们一个小时后就回来
We'll be back in an hour.
小卡  恭喜  同性婚姻万岁
Hey, Cam. Congratulations. Go, gay marriage.
他又吐了
He did it again.
是吗
Ay, si?
好吧
Okay. Well...
m 20 0 l 209 0 b 218 0 229 11 229 20 l 229 209 b 229 218 218 228 209 228 l 20 228 b 11 228 0 218 0 209 l 0 20 b 0 11 11 0 20 0
m 115 64 l 115 35 l 171 0 l 177 0 l 133 46 l 143 52 l 179 0 l 184 0 l 159 63 l 229 107 l 229 182 l 145 96 l 135 122 l 207 227 l 137 227 l 115 172 l 115 93 l 126 76 l 115 64 l 104 76 l 115 93 l 115 172 l 93 227 l 23 227 l 95 122 l 84 96 l 0 182 l 0 107 l 70 63 l 45 0 l 50 0 l 87 52 l 97 46 l 52 0 l 59 0 l 115 35
m 71 60 b 71 0 161 0 161 60 b 161 120 71 120 71 60
m 325 0 l 355 0 l 332 47 l 354 47 l 399 136 l 369 136 l 328 53 l 288 136 l 257 136 l 325 0 m 467 0 l 497 0 l 474 47 l 496 47 l 541 136 l 511 136 l 470 53 l 430 136 l 399 136 l 467 0 m 545 1 l 583 1 l 583 14 l 568 14 l 568 19 l 583 19 l 583 30 l 568 30 l 568 34 l 599 34 l 599 30 l 583 30 l 583 19 l 599 19 l 599 14 l 583 14 l 583 1 l 611 1 b 616 1 622 6 622 10 l 622 36 l 652 0 l 678 0 l 644 41 l 622 41 l 622 47 l 596 47 l 597 54 l 625 54 l 625 68 l 541 68 l 541 54 l 572 54 l 571 47 l 545 47 l 545 1 m 583 72 l 583 85 l 569 85 l 569 90 l 598 90 l 598 85 l 583 85 l 583 72 l 611 72 b 615 72 621 78 621 82 l 653 44 l 678 44 l 644 86 l 621 86 l 621 103 l 597 103 l 597 136 l 570 136 l 564 126 l 562 136 l 542 136 l 548 107 l 568 107 l 565 121 l 571 121 l 571 103 l 547 103 l 547 72 l 583 72 m 600 107 l 620 107 l 624 124 l 653 89 l 679 89 l 642 136 l 615 136 l 618 132 l 606 132 l 600 107 m 689 0 l 716 0 l 721 15 l 732 15 l 732 30 l 718 56 l 731 56 l 735 100 l 721 100 l 717 59 l 714 64 l 714 136 l 693 136 l 693 79 l 676 79 l 707 30 l 679 30 l 679 15 l 694 15 l 689 0 m 738 0 l 804 0 b 807 0 813 6 813 9 l 813 87 l 794 87 l 794 14 l 756 14 l 756 87 l 763 77 l 763 21 l 787 21 l 787 91 l 798 91 l 798 120 l 820 120 l 812 136 l 778 136 l 778 90 l 748 136 l 723 136 l 756 87 l 738 87 l 738 0 m 257 151 l 275 151 l 297 182 l 319 151 l 337 151 l 304 197 l 304 227 l 290 227 l 290 197 l 257 151 m 337 151 l 355 151 l 377 182 l 399 151 l 417 151 l 384 197 l 384 227 l 370 227 l 370 197 l 337 151 m 425 192 l 447 192 b 445 181 427 181 425 192 l 410 192 b 414 162 458 162 462 192 l 462 206 l 425 206 b 425 210 429 212 433 213 l 462 213 l 462 227 l 433 227 b 412 227 408 203 410 192 m 462 151 l 532 151 l 532 165 l 504 165 l 504 227 l 489 227 l 489 165 l 462 165 l 462 151 m 580 172 l 580 186 l 549 186 b 543 186 543 192 549 192 l 565 192 b 589 192 589 227 565 227 l 532 227 l 532 213 l 565 213 b 570 213 570 206 565 206 l 549 206 b 524 206 524 172 549 172 l 580 172 m 592 213 l 606 213 l 606 227 l 592 227 l 592 213 m 639 172 l 665 172 l 665 186 l 639 186 b 623 186 623 213 639 213 l 665 213 l 665 227 l 639 227 b 603 227 603 172 639 172 m 700 184 b 722 184 722 215 700 215 l 700 229 b 740 229 740 170 700 170 b 660 170 660 229 700 229 l 700 215 b 680 215 680 184 700 184 m 737 172 l 782 172 b 803 172 813 177 813 198 l 813 228 l 799 228 l 799 198 b 799 186 793 187 782 187 l 782 228 l 768 228 l 768 187 l 752 187 l 752 228 l 737 228 l 737 172
人人影视
YYeTs.com
原创翻译  双语字幕
■
仅供学习 禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
更多影视更新
请登陆www.YYeTs.com
翻译：威廉  山谬  冰蓝  3CC醉芝士
时间轴：加森    校对：olivia_xuxu   后期&总监：瓜瓜
摩  登
家  庭
第五季 第一集
跟我讲讲  小卡
So tell me, Cam.
你们男男之间是怎么"攻做"的
How does it work when it is between two men?
我觉得在莉莉面前
Well, I don't really feel comfortable
谈论这种事不太好吧
talking about that... in front of Lily.
我知道你们怎么做的啦
I know how that works.
有次我租错碟了
I rented the wrong movie once.
你看过《"大根"游戏》吗
Did you see "Glen, Garry, Glenn, and Ross"?
恶搞阿尔・帕西诺主演的《大亨游戏》
没有
Uh, no.
-你先去一边玩  -我的问题是
- Why don't you go play? - What I mean is,
谁该向谁求婚呢
who proposes to who?
我不知道  我们谈过如果合法了要怎样
I don't know. We've talked about it, if it ever became legal.
现在成真了  你今天要求婚吗
Okay, and now it is. So are you going to do it today?
才刚刚宣布
Well, it just happened.
我还没有...
I haven't really had...
你一定要今天求婚
Oh, you have to do it today.
每对爱人都应该有段美好的求婚故事
Every couple deserve a beautiful proposal story.
我一直很羡慕我爸妈的求婚故事
Well, I have always adored my mom and dad's story.
我爸用犁在我妈窗外的雪地里
He plowed "Will you marry me?" into a snowy field
犁出了"你愿意嫁给我吗"几个字
right outside of her window.
他们结婚25周年时
And then he tried to re-create it
他想再重现那个场景
for their 25th wedding anniversary.
但当时没下雪  他把字烧在玉米地里了
But there was no snow, so he burned it into a cornfield.
大错特错
Bad idea.
但我妈确实因此又得到一枚戒指
You know, but mama did get a second ring out of it
用紧急事务管理署发的救援金买的
with the F.E.M.A. money.
我多希望自己也有浪漫的故事
Ay, I wish I also had a romantic story.
那天  我们在饭前看电视
One day, we were watching tv before dinner,
杰说  "曼尼  把东西给我"
and Jay says, "Manny, hand me that thing."
曼尼就把戒指递过去了
And Manny gives him the ring.
当然  我很开心
I mean, I was very happy, of course,
但我总想经历更好的故事
but it is not the best story.
至少哈维尔还是骑着海豚求婚的
At least Javier was on top of a dolphin.
战士们总谈论将一切抛之脑后的那一刻
Soldiers talk about that moment when they shut off,
在战争终于结束的时候
when the war finally wins.
-蹲下  -闭嘴吧你
- Get down! - Shut up!
我看不到电视了
I can't see the tv!
把风扇打开
Turn the fan on!
别鬼叫了  我脑袋都要炸了
Oh, stop yelling! My head's going to explode!
对我来说  那一刻就是
For me, that moment is
暑假开始的第四天
four days into summer vacation.
亲爱的  怎么了
Hey, honey. What's up?
你还能想起当夏天只有萤火虫
Do you remember when summer meant fireflies
热裤以及冰淇淋的时候吗
and cutoff shorts and ice-cream trucks?
我有其中之一
Well, one out of three.
会有时间的  他们都要出门的  对吧
We'll get our time. They're all going away at some point, right?
是啊  海莉要去海滨
Yeah, Haley's got her beach trip,
艾丽克斯要参加国际仁人家园活动
and Alex is doing Habitat for Humanity,
卢克要去露营
and Luke has camp.
没记错的话
If I remember,
我们有六个小时清静独处的时间
I think we have six hours totally kid-free on...
就在14号那天
oh, the 14th.
如果我们更改艾丽克斯的航班
Hey, if we moved Alex's flight,
我们就能有10或12个小时了
we could have, like, 10 or 12 hours.
有点野心  热裤男
Dream bigger, hot pants.
靠边
Step aside.
有时我不知道自己是喜欢怕克莱尔的感觉
Sometimes I don't know if I love how much I fear Claire,
还是怕自己太爱她
or fear how much I love her.
把艾丽克斯从22号调到8号
22nd to the 8th for Alex,
把卢克调到14号
Luke to the 14th,
把海莉调到这天
Haley gets a day there.
-好嘞  -就是这样  真是大智慧
- Come on. - That's it, beautiful mind.
化疯狂为美好
Harness that crazy into something positive.
如果能让艾丽克斯把仁人家园活动的地点
Shh! If I can get Alex to move her Habitat for Humanity
从俄克拉荷马州调到萨克拉门托
from Oklahoma to Sacramento
再让卢克更改露营的日期
and Luke to move his camp session,
他们就会和海莉的出游时间重合
they will both overlap with Haley's vacation,
那样我们就有7天自由时间了
and I just bought us seven kid-free days.
-点"时"成金啊  -是的
- Witchcraft! - Yes.
我崇拜死自己了  歌洛莉亚
I've outdone myself, Gloria.
我订了我们第一次约会的餐厅
I booked the restaurant from our first date,
依然是那张能俯瞰大海的桌子
the same table overlooking the ocean,
我会在日落时分开口
and I'll do it at sunset,
我最近发现日落时的光线最衬我了
which I've recently discovered is my ideal lighting.
真浪漫啊
That's so romantic.
是啊  很浪漫吧
I know! Isn't it?
是米奇尔打来的
Oh, okay. Oh, that's Mitchell.
我要挂了
Gotta go.
别让他听出来你有多兴奋
Oh, don't let him hear the excitement in your voice.
你说得对  说得对
You're right. You're right.
-说话  -我在三街的咖啡店
- What? - I'm at that coffee shop on 3rd,
我忘记带钱包了
and I forgot my wallet.
能来救我吗
Can you come bail me out?
怎么这么巧啊
Ugh. Isn't this convenient?
其实真的很巧  我离那里只有两条街
It actually was. I was only two blocks away.
但我到了以后  发现是他为了求婚
But when I got there, I realized it was all a ploy
耍的小伎俩
so he could propose.
但他这么做真贴心
But it was so sweet,
我决定放弃自己的计划让他先下手了
I just decided to ditch my plans and let him do it.
米奇尔  太抱歉了
Mitchell, I'm so sorry,
但405公路上发生了严重追尾事件
But there is a massive pileup on the 405,
我得去接莉莉了
and, well, I have to go pick up Lily.
也许你可以给克莱尔打电话求助
And maybe you could just call Claire or something?
小卡  小卡  我大概还剩50美分
Cam, Cam, I got, like, 50 cents to my name.
你决定点什么茶了吗
Have you decided on a tea?
价格都一样吗
Do they all cost the same?
好吧
Yeah.
好长的队啊
Look at that line.
大家可能都来领同性结婚证书了
Probably everybody getting their gay marriage license.
那好像就叫结婚证书吧
I think it's just called a marriage license.
那个  我也说不清
Yeah, I don't know.
也许我们该回家  不去了
Maybe we should go home and forget about it.
什么
What?
我最近在阅读一些热带疾病的资料
I've been reading up on some of those tropical diseases --
疟疾  黄热病  狂犬病
Malaria, yellow fever, rabies.
我属于高危人群  杰
I'm high risk, Jay.
我喜欢与人握手
I'm a big hand shaker.
没事的  你注射过所有疫苗了
You're fine. You've had all your shots.
而且你喷的帕科香水会吓跑蚊子的
And that Paco Rabanne will scare away any mosquitoes.
杰  我害怕
Jay, I'm scared.
我不确定自己想不想去了
I'm not sure I want to go through with it.
我们开了这么远的路来拿证明
We didn't drive all the way down here for that piece of paper
可不是为了让你临阵脱逃的
for you to get cold feet at the last second.
到底发生了什么事
And what happened, anyway?
你几个月来一直很盼望这一天
You've been looking forward to this day for months.
我知道  但也许我们该等到明年
I know. But maybe we should wait until next year.
我现在还太小了
I'm still kind of young to be doing this.
不能等
We're not waiting.
我已经付钱了  你妈妈也签字了
I already paid for you, and your mother signed off.
就这么定了
This is happening.
好日子  是吧
Great day, huh?
-我来了  -谢天谢地
- Hello! - Oh, thank god.
我喝了好多杯茶
I've had so many cups of tea,
他们给了我专属的厕所钥匙
they gave me my own one of these.
给你
Ohh. Here you go.
恭喜你们终于可以合法结婚了
So congratulations on the whole marriage thing.
-太棒了  对吧  -是啊
- How amazing is that, right? - Yeah.
你们很快就要举办一场同性恋婚礼了吗
We gonna hear some big gay wedding bells soon?
叫婚礼就可以了
Ah, well, just wedding bells.
当然啦  我们总是讨论这事
Yeah. Yeah, of course. We've always talked about it.
但你知道的
But, you know,
只是要找到合适的时机
it's just -- just a matter of finding the right timing.
还有其它的一些因素
And then there -- there's a couple of other factors --
税务影响和财产规划
the tax implications and estate planning.
打住  我都要晕了
Oh, stop. I'm swooning.
我只是从实际考虑
I'm just being practical.
你也是这样的人啊
You're the same way.
你叫菲尔退掉订婚戒指
You -- you told Phil to take back your engagement ring
买台洗衣烘干机
and buy you a washer/dryer.
别扯到我身上来  拜托
Well, don't put this back on me. Come on.
小卡最不满意你哪一点
What is Cam's biggest complaint about you?
你不浪漫
You're not romantic.
现在是你翻身的大好时机
This is your opportunity.
米奇尔  你今晚回家
Mitchell, you should go home tonight
隆重地向他求婚  给他一个惊喜
and surprise him with a big, splashy proposal.
如果我向他求婚  他会很开心的
He would really like it if I proposed to him.
我想下班后我可以去买张卡片
I guess I could stop after work and pick up a card.
-然后  -天啊  你简直无可救药
- And... - Oh, my god. You're hopeless.
-我知道  -米奇尔
- I know. - Mitchell, okay.
-你要这样做  -天啊
- This is what you do. - Oh, boy.
但是该由你自己想主意
It really should be your own idea, though.
不  拜托  我需要帮助  求你了
No! Come on, come on. I need help. Please?
好吧
Fine. Okay.
今晚  你给他做他最爱吃的菜肴
Tonight, you cook him his favorite meal.
开一瓶最好的红酒
You open the best bottle of wine.
当你们坐着品味美酒时
And just as the two of you are sitting down to enjoy it,
你和他分手
you break up with him.
什么  为什么
What? Why?
因为在他伤心欲绝的时候
Because then, as he is at his lowest,
你突然求婚
you pop the question.
他会从痛苦不堪变成欢天喜地
He goes from agony to ecstasy!
多浪漫
It's so romantic.
你在开玩笑  对吧
You're kidding, right?
你想要更传统的吗  好吧
More traditional? Okay.
好  你深情凝视他的双眼
All right. You look into his eyes...
说  "我去看了医生
And you say, "I saw a doctor.
他发现了一小块黑色的东西"
He found a small dark mass."
你什么毛病啊
What are you?
当他开始哭泣时
And then just as he begins to cry,
你拿出一个装着戒指的黑盒子
you pull out a black box with a ring in it.
这就是那个黑色的东西
There's your small dark mass!
这主意太天才了
It's genius!
你真是个灾难
Y-you're a disaster.
你也可以走灾难路线
You could go the disaster route, too.
你听过我是怎么告诉菲尔我怀上卢克的吗
Did you ever hear how I told Phil we were gonna have Luke?
我说"每天都有成千上万的儿童死去"
I said, "Thousands of children die every day..."
爸
Dad?
抱歉  我太为你自豪而吵到你了吗
I'm sorry. Was I being proud of you too loud?
你在干什么
What are you doing?
做仁人家园志愿者  去帮助别人
Going off to habitat, helping all those people.
乖女儿  我简直无语凝噎了
Honey, I'm speechless.
谢谢  我只是觉得那...
Thanks. I just thought it was --
但你确定要去俄克拉荷马州吗
But are we sure about Oklahoma?
在萨克拉门托就有许多需要帮助的人
There's so many needy people right up in Sacramento.
从家开车就能到那里
And it's driving distance.
我已经确认了我的工作细节
I already signed up for my work detail,
也开始和同住一个帐篷的人邮件联系了
and I've been e-mailing with my tentmate.
是啊  你说得对
Yeah. No, you're right.
我想只是...
I guess it's just...
不
No.
算了
Never mind.
怎么了
What is it?
没事  这太愚蠢了
No, it's stupid.
只是我以前从没
I've just never been so far away
离我的小女儿这么远
from my baby girl before.
现在别哭啊  别哭
Not now, waterworks. Not now.
老爸
Oh, daddy.
你还好吗  爸
You okay, dad?
你好啊  孩子  我很好
Oh, hey, buddy. Never been better.
你真是体贴
You're so thoughtful.
你14号去露营后我会想念你的好的
I'm gonna miss that when you go off to camp on the 14th.
来打威浮高尔夫吗
Little Wiffle golf?
等等  我14号没法去露营
Wait. I cant't go to camp on the 14th.
我得和卡莉一起去
I have to go when Carly's going.
卡莉是谁
Who's Carly?
她是我喜欢的女孩  她就在客厅呢
She's this girl I like, and she's here right now.
那就更应该改变露营的日期了
Well, all the more reason to change camp sessions.
小别胜新婚嘛  这是不会错的
Absence makes the heart grow fonder. It's foolproof.
这次会错  你别想了
Not this fool. Forget it.
你还会遇见很多新女孩的
What about all the new girls you're gonna meet?
你才14岁
You're only 14.
现在就想吊死在一棵树上了吗
Do you really want to be tied down?
是的
Yes!
卢克  瞧  我会了  好
Oh, Luke, watch. I-I got it. Okay.
好
Okay.
真棒
Nice!
您好  邓菲先生
Oh, hi, Mr. Dunphy.
抱歉我们搬开了家具
Sorry we moved the furniture around.
我给卢克表演了
I was showing Luke
我在翻筋斗地区赛上做的动作
the flip I did at tumbling sectionals.
不好  是我妈妈来了
Oh, no. That's my mom.
但我可以把我带来的这部老电影留给你们
But I can leave you guys this old movie I brought over.
电影名是《辣身舞》
It's called "Dirty Dancing."
千万别放开她
Never let her go.
你好  卡莉妈妈  我是菲尔・邓菲
Hey, Carly's mom. Phil Dunphy.
你女儿的铁杆粉
Big fan of your daughter.
-谢谢你  -放开我
- Thank you. - Get off me!
听我说  卢克得改变露营的日期
So, yeah, heads up. Luke's got to change his camp session.
-你们能不能也改一改  -不行
- You guys may want to do the same. - No.
我丈夫和我这周都在算计日程
My husband and I have been working the white board all week,
好不容易能离开这些熊孩子三天
and we just bought three days away from that.
-又不是我干的  -你也打过去
- It wasn't even me! - Bank it!
卡莉
Carly!
曼尼  记住  你下了飞机
Okay, Manny, remember, as soon as you land,
就留神点玛拉莉亚[疟疾]
watch out for Malaria.
为什么  我打过疫苗了
Why? I got a shot for that.
我们能快点吗
Can we hurry this up?
不  我说的是你表姐玛拉莉亚
No, I'm talking about your cousin Malaria.
她去接你  但她可能带露贝拉一起去
She's coming to pick you up, but she might have Rubella.
-什么  -那是她女儿的名字
- What? - That's her daughter.
但在车上离她远点儿
But make room in the car
因为她可能有白喉
because she could have diphtheria.
谁是白喉
Who's diphtheria?
曼尼  白喉是一种病
Ay, Manny, diphtheria is a disease.
所以我要你在车上离她远点儿
That's why I want you to be apart from her in the car.
好了  走吧  歌洛莉亚  该告别了
Okay, let's go. Gloria, better say goodbye here.
他得抓紧去过安检了
He's got to hurry to get through security.
-又没有排长队  -马上就要排了
- But there's no line. - For now.
一队老年人旅游团刚到
A senior tour bus just pulled up.
你知道他们会让警报响多少回吗
You know how much private wanding that is?
他们身上一半的骨头都是金属的
Half their skeletons are metal.
曼尼  一降落就打给我哦
Ay, Manny, please. Call me as soon as you land.
-我会想你的  -走吧走吧
- I'll miss you. - And we're walking.
我爱你
I love you!
-慢着  -不  快上去
- Wait. - No. Up!
我忘了把我写的卡片给妈妈了
I forgot to give mom this card I wrote.
别别别  我帮你给她
Uh, no, no, no. I'll handle it.
一路平安  伙计  一路平安
Safe trip, buddy. Safe trip.
我们走啦
We're out of here.
别  我要目送他上楼
No, let's wait until he gets to the top.
保重  我的宝贝
Adios, mi amor!
谁想吃冰淇淋
Who wants ice cream? Huh?
他要是不回来了怎么办
What if he never comes back?
宝贝  哪有人离开家会不回来啊
Oh, honey, no one ever leaves home and doesn't come back.
我就是啊
I did.
乖女儿
Hey, honey.
我一直在考虑你去萨克拉门托的决定
I've been mulling over your Sacramento decision.
实际上那不是我的决...
It wasn't exactly my --
当然  我希望宝贝女儿离家近点儿
Of course I want my baby girl close,
但我得习惯你离家在外
but I got to get used to you leaving.
因为你上大学  而且肯定是名牌大学
Because college -- and knowing you, a great college --
已经指日可待了
is right around the corner.
我没说错吧
Am I right?
参加国际仁人家园会给你的大学申请加分
Now, habitat will look good on an application,
但萨克拉门托这地方真的对你有帮助吗
but does Sacramento really move the needle?
我在考虑另一个地方
I have another place in mind.
给你点提示  地名以"萨尔"开头
Little hint -- it starts with an "El."
萨尔瓦多吗  你开玩笑吧
El Salvador? Are you serious?
那地方政局不稳定
They have an unstable government
还是地震高发区
and -- and earthquakes.
看这有船  好像还有山呢
Boats. Looks like there's a h-hill.
我只是想说  你如果这个关头不逼自己
I'm just saying, you don't push yourself at this stage,
就只能上二流大学了
you wind up at a second-tier college.
很快你就会失去你的抱负
Soon you've lost all your ambition.
你会一辈子碌碌无为
You're just drifting through life,
指望有人给你个"家庭主妇"文凭
hoping someone offers you an "M-r-s" Degree.
那是你想要的生活吗
Is that who you want to be?
我的公主  第二顿早餐吗
Hey, princess. Second breakfast?
有意思
Fun.
马上要去海滩了是吧
So, big beach trip coming up, huh?
是的
Yeah.
没什么比七月底更好的了
Can't get better than late July,
-除了八月初  -省省吧  老爸
- unless it's early Aug... - Save it, dad.
我知道你和妈妈想摆脱我们独占房子
I know you and mom want the house to yourselves.
不是的
Nope.
就差我还没搞定了  对吧
I'm the last piece of the puzzle, right?
开个价吧
What's it worth to you?
好吧
Fine.
我给你付油钱和两顿饭行不
How about I pay for gas and two dinners?
不够  汽油费
Mnh-mnh. Gas,
每顿饭  日用品  两套新泳装
All dinners, groceries, two new bathing suits,
-冲浪板  还有...  -你疯了吗
- a boogie board, one of those... - Are you crazy?
-不  我还没说完呢  -你完了
- No. I'm also not done. - Yes, you are done.
知道为什么吗
You know why?
知道还有个结果是什么吗
You know another way this shakes out?
就是不让你去
You don't go.
没错  你要是太过分  你爹我不干了
That's right. Overplay your hand, I pull the plug,
你就失去了最后一次和朋友逍遥的机会
you blow your last chance for a good time with your friends.
大家会说你这人真没劲
Word gets out that you're not cool.
然后开学了
Then school starts.
你只好一整年死读书
You end up with your nose in a book all year.
交不到朋友  钓不到帅哥
No friends, no dates,
从来不打扮
not caring how you look.
那是你想要的生活吗
Is that who you want to be?
原来米奇尔真的是忘带钱包
Turns out Mitchell really had forgotten his wallet,
所以他根本没想到求婚的事
so proposing wasn't even on his radar.
我的计划无懈可击
My plan was bulletproof.
他会像创始人日上
He was gonna be as blindsided
最肥的猪一样被蒙在鼓里
as the fattest hog on Founder's Day,
而我呢
And I was...
真为我自己自豪
Pretty darn proud of myself.
我有个理想的求婚计划
I had the ideal proposal.
小卡曾经告诉我  他想要的就是
Cam once told me that all he wanted
一个能和他一起坐在摇椅上慢慢变老的人
was someone to sit in a rocking chair and grow old with.
所以我们吃晚饭时
So while we're at dinner,
克莱尔会去准备两把摇椅
Claire is setting up two rocking chairs
放在壁炉旁  再配上一瓶香槟
next to the fireplace, with a bottle of champagne.
他一定会...
Ohh. He is going to...
像四人扔猪游戏里的
Squeal like a Berkshire white
伯克郡猪一样尖叫不止
in a four-man pig toss.
天啊  我太想念创始人日了
Gosh durn it, I miss Founder's Day.
来这里吃简餐也太铺张了吧
This is a little bit fancy for just a quick bite.
没准都没有位子呢
Well, who knows if they can even get us in?
我问问看
Let me check.
塔克订的位
Reservation for Tucker.
东西都布置好了吗
Is everything set up with the table?
有位
Yeah.
那是我们第一次约会的餐厅
The restaurant where we had our first date,
还有小卡最爱的日落霞光
the sunset lighting that Cam loves...
他这是要求婚的节奏啊
He was going to propose.
我太感动了
I-I-I was so touched,
但同时  他也在摧毁我唯一的
but at the same time, he was ruining the one chance I had
展现浪漫情怀的机会
for romantic redemption.
小卡  我觉得很恶心
Oh, I'm feeling really queasy, Cam.
没事没事  我们坐下你就好了
No, no, no. You'll be okay once we sit down.
我想我得回家  对不起
I think I need to go home. Sorry.
不好意思  对不起
Oh! S-- excuse me. Sorry.
没事没事  我给你要点姜汁和饼干
No, no, no. We'll get you some ginger ale, some crackers.
不行  我得直奔厕所了
Mnh-mnh. I'm -- I got to run to the restroom.
你去取车吧
You -- you grab the car.
你吐完就好受了
Well, you'll feel better after you throw up.
计划有变  我们会提早回来
Okay, new plan. We're coming back early.
都准备好了吗
Is everything set up?
你说要两小时才回来的  我们还没出发
You said two hours. We haven't even left yet.
-那赶紧啊  -拖延一下
- Well, hurry! - Just stall.
就跟他说  海莉大出血了
Tell him that... Haley had a hemorrhage,
而只有你和她血型一致
and you're her blood type,
-所以你  -我才不要  你个食尸鬼
- so you... - I'm not doing that, you ghoul.
快去家里准备
Just get back to the house and --
-歌洛莉亚  -小卡  怎样啦
- Gloria. - Cam, how did it go?
-他有没有  -没成功
- Did he... - It didn't happen.
得实施后备方案了
I have to go with the backup plan.
幸好我有个后备的求婚方案
Fortunately, I had an alternate proposal scenario
以备不时之需
in case there was a problem.
杰和歌洛莉亚在帮忙看孩子
Jay and Gloria were babysitting,
于是我让他们重现
so I asked them to re-create
我们搬进我们的第一间公寓
the picnic under the stars we had
那晚在星空下共进野餐的情景
the night we moved in to our first apartment.
米奇尔肯定一看到就会...
Mitchell would take one look and...
像获了托尼奖一样喜极而泣
Sob like a Tony winner.
我找到了野餐篮
I got the picnic basket.
但你知道什么东西很难找吗
But you know what is going to be hard to find?
我对这整件闹剧的兴趣吗
My interest in this whole damn thing?
不  是蓝白色的桌布
No, the blue-and-white tablecloth.
找到了  在特殊场合用品柜里
Here it is. It was in the occasions closet.
他们把工具放在枕头套里
They keep their tools in a pillowcase,
却用整个柜子来放特殊场合用品吗
but they have an occasions closet?
你们怎么在这里
What are you guys doing here?
小卡要向米奇求婚
Oh. Cam is going to propose to Mitch,
我们在帮他布场
so we're here to help him set it up.
太巧了
That is coconuts!
米奇尔也叫我们来做一样的事
Mitchell asked us to do the same thing for him.
这样一来我真想留下
Well, that just makes me want to stay
看看结果会怎样
and see how this whole thing works out.
可以啊  我们布好场  然后躲起来
Oh, we can. Let's set it up and then we'll hide somewhere.
没错  躲进特殊场合用品柜里
Ay, yes, in the occasion closet.
不行  我们就照吩咐办  然后离开
No. We do what they asked and leave.
我们那辈人从没有过这种烦恼
We never had these problems.
这就是允许男人和男人结婚的下场
This is what happens when they let men marry men.
那肯定不是巧合
That cannot be a coincidence.
不好意思  我绕了路
Sorry about the detour.
我担心405公路上会塞车
I was just worried about the pileup on the 405.
慢慢开  坐车反而让我舒服些了
Oh, take your time. The drive's actually soothing me.
我的天
Oh! Oh, my gosh!
搞什么  怎么回事
Oh! What -- what was that?
我想是爆胎了  没事的
Oh. I think it's a blown tire. It's okay.
还有备胎  有工具吗
Well, I know there's a spare. Do -- do we have the tools?
-有的  在后备箱的枕头套里  -好
- Yeah, yeah. They're in the pillowcase in the trunk. - Right.
你为什么要这样不耐烦
Why do you have to be so grouchy?
我们在为他们创造美好的故事
We're giving them a beautiful story.
每个人都值得拥有一个美好回忆
Everybody deserves one.
我是个白痴
I'm an idiot.
你不是白痴  你不像别人那样浪漫
Oh, you're not an idiot. You're not as romantic as some --
这些东西背面就有双面胶
These things peel off on the back,
而我还一直在用胶水粘
and I've been gluing 'em.
我费个什么劲  你根本不在乎这些感觉
Why do I even bother? You don't care about this stuff.
你这是什么意思
What's that supposed to mean?
就像你向我求婚的时候
Yeah, like when you proposed to me.
你说"曼尼  把那个东西给我"
"Hey, Manny, hand me that thing."
那就是我的故事
That's my whole story.
慢着  那不是我的错
Hang on. That wasn't my fault.
我本来安排好了
I had something big planned.
你叫他把戒指给你
You asked him for the ring.
我指的是遥控器  他自己偷跑了
I was asking for the remote. He jumped the gun.
他本该在当天晚些时候
He was supposed to give me the ring
在餐厅里把戒指递给我的
later that night at the restaurant.
服务员会来问我们要不要咖啡
The waiter was gonna come by and offer coffee.
我会说"不用了  谢谢  喝了睡不着
I was gonna say, "No, thank you. It'll keep me up,
这段时间  我一直活在梦中
and lately, I've been loving my dreams,
有一个梦  我希望能成为现实"
and there's one in particular I hope comes true."
然后曼尼会把戒指给我
Manny gives me the ring.
我说  "歌洛莉亚"
I say, "Gloria --"
我愿意  杰  我愿意嫁给你
Yes, Jay! Yes, I marry you!
我喜欢我的新故事
I love my new story.
提醒下  我绝对会在他们的婚礼上哭的
Little heads-up -- there's no way I'm not crying at this wedding.
菲尔  你来这里的路上就哭了
Phil, you cried on the way here.
我当时已经泪在眼眶了
I was on the brink already.
我出门前看了《辣身舞》
I watched "Dirty Dancing" before we left.
我爸的短信
Text from my dad.
不好
Oh, no.
他要我过去看望他几天
He wants me to come visit him for a couple of days,
正好是孩子们都出门的那周
but it's right in the middle of our kid-free week.
太可惜了  我想你去两天没问题
Oh, that's too bad. I guess you could take two days.
我可能跟弗兰克说过
I may have mentioned to Frank
菲尔那周可能有空
that Phil might be available that week.
唯一比孩子们都出门更棒的
The only thing better than a kid-free week
就是再挤出几天让我独处
is a couple of days carved out just for mama.
完美
Perfect.
是的
Yeah.
还记得我向你求婚的那天吗
Hey, you remember the day I proposed to you?
当然记得
Of course I do.
我不太记得是哪一天了  但我记得
I don't remember the exact date, but, yes.
1994年3月19日
March 19, 1994.
是哦
Oh. Yeah.
那天下午我心情相当不好
I was in such a bad mood that afternoon.
圣帕特里克节喝醉后的第二天宿醉
I was on day two of a St. Patrick's hangover.
我不记得这点
I don't remember that.
我只记得我爱得有多疯狂
I just remember how crazy in love I was.
我等不及想向你求婚
I couldn't wait to ask you.
去接你的路上甚至闯了个红灯
I even ran a red light on the way to pick you up.
罚单我还留着
I still have the ticket.
不可能  你为什么要说这样的话
No, you don't. Why would you say something like that?
开什么玩笑  我在冲向我的新人生
Are you kidding me? I was racing to my life.
罚单就在我爸家
It's in a box at my dad's
和其他东西存在一个盒子里
with a bunch of other stuff --
包括你我相识的那场音乐会的节目单
The program from that concert where I met you...
你给我的写着假电话号码的火柴盒
...the matchbook with the fake number on it you gave me...
我们第一次约会的纪念酒杯
The souvenir goblet from our first date.
你觉得我会把这些美好回忆扔掉吗
You really think I'd throw away all those beautiful memories...
我的夫人
...milady?
我已经很久没再看看那些东西了
I haven't seen that stuff for a long time.
我去见我爸时一定要翻出来
I got to dig it out when I see my dad.
好了  别说了  对不起
Okay, stop. Sorry.
怎么了
What?
我让你爸爸找你的
I told your dad to call you
因为我想有几天单独清静的时间
because I wanted some time for myself.
是的  几天远离我那完美浪漫的丈夫
Yeah, couple of days away from my perfect, romantic husband,
我这个铁石心肠
who is far too good
冷血无情的机器人根本配不上的好丈夫
for this cold-hearted, bloodless wife-bot.
你不冷血
You have blood.
亲爱的  我只是把椅子放在了火炉前
Honey, I just put the chairs in front of the fireplace.
你却布置得这么浪漫
You made it romantic.
米奇尔说得对  我是个食尸鬼
Mitchell's right. I'm a ghoul.
过来
Come here.
你有你自己有趣的浪漫方式
You're romantic, too, in your own funny way.
我们只是不同
We're just different.
我更多愁善感些又如何
So what if I'm more sentimental?
是我妈
My mom.
我是说  当然
I mean, sure...
婚姻需要浪漫
Marriage needs romance.
知道还需要什么吗
You know what it also needs?
"菲尔联系过我  他建议..."
"Spoke to Phil, and he suggested --"
宽容
Forgiveness.
好了  请给我备胎
Okay. Spare, please.
是的  医生
Yes, doctor.
真不敢相信我们碰到这种事太多次了
I can't believe this has happened to us so many times,
居然有了换胎的固定程序
we actually have a system.
我知道  从你第一次看到千斤顶
Oh, I know. You've come a long way
这一路走来你可不容易
from the first time you ever saw a jack.
记得吗  你不相信...
Remember, you couldn't believe...
抱歉  这真是太棒了
I'm sorry. This is amazing.
我正在抬起一辆车
I am lifting a car right now.
我是全世界最强壮的男人
I am the strongest man in the world.
还记得那次在约塞米蒂国家公园
Oh, do you remember that time in Yosemite
雪下得非常大吗
when it was snowing so bad?
记得  那是六年前吗
Yeah. What was that, like six years ago?
老天  不  是在领养莉莉之前
Oh, gosh. No, it was before Lily,
所以至少有七八年了
so it was at least seven or eight.
老天  时间过得真快
God, it is -- it's going by so fast.
对  那还用说
Yeah. You're telling me.
知道吗  24小时之前  这下面
You know, it's a different world down there
是一个完全不同的世界
than it was 24 hours ago.
小卡  轮胎  轮胎
Cam, tire. Tire!
老天  我的天  我的天
Oh, my gosh. Oh, my -- oh, my god.
我的天
Oh, my god!
对住在那个黄色房子里的人来说
It's gonna be a different world
世界也将要变得不同了
for the people in that yellow house.
我今晚的计划绝对不是这样的
This is not at all how I saw the evening going.
亲爱的  你绝对想不到
Honey, you have no idea.
你还记得我们的第一间公寓吗
Do you remember our first apartment?
记得  你怎么想到那个了
Yes. What -- what made you think of that?
我不知道
I don't know.
星空
The stars.
好了  来吧  换胎
All right. Come on. Let's do this.
好
Yeah.
-我愿意  -我愿意
- Yes. - Yes.
大腿上有星星的这位美女
Hey, there, you with the stars on your thighs.
-什么  -是首老歌  我是想...
- Huh? - It's an old song. I thought I would...
我费个什么劲
Eh, why do I bother?
-这是什么  -曼尼给的
- What is this? - Oh. Oh, that's from Manny.
我本想过几天再给你
I was hoping to wait and give it to you in a couple of days.
你要记住他很好
But, uh, just remember that he's fine.
他离你的距离坐飞机就能到
He's only a plane ride away.
不错
Nice.
我去洗脸了
I'm going to wash my face.
好的
Okay.
希望我的表兄弟姐妹们不要带他去骑马
I hope that my cousins don't take him riding the horses
或是玩枪
or shooting the guns.
我知道他已经算是个成年男人了  但
I know that he's almost a man, but...
杰
Jay?
"你要照顾好杰
"Make sure you take care of Jay.
他周四体检后请给我打电话
Please call me after his checkup on Thursday.
我会非常想你们的"
I'll miss you guys so much."
真懂事  是吧
Nice, huh?
只是懂事吗
Nice?
我去把他的另一件睡袍寄给他
I'm gonna mail him his other robe.